Abraham: Let's have a look at some
of the core terminology used in cyber
security, starting with Software.
Nicole: We all know that software
consists of instructions that
tell a computer system what to do.
It is everything to do with the computer
that isn’t hardware, [the physical
components of a system.] Software can be
a set of programs compiled into a package
such as Internet browser, operating
system and general programs used to run
a computer, as well as complex systems
used for companies and organisations.
Without the software the
hardware wouldn’t run.
Abraham: However, software can
also attack a computer and its
systems in the form of Malware.
This is an umbrella term that describes
all forms of malicious software including
viruses, trojans, worms and ransomware.
It can be used to steal information
or damage a system for malicious
reasons or just for financial gain.
Anti-malware is key to keeping
systems secure against attack.
Nicole: DoS and DDoS attacks
involve the ‘denial of service’
to the owner of the system.
In a DoS attack a computer is used
to flood or crash a system with too
much internet traffic causing it
to slow down and eventually stop.
This can be managed by using firewalls
at key points in a network [multiple
computers and devices connected together].
Firewalls are network security devices
that monitor, and filter incoming
and outgoing network traffic based on
previously established security policies.
They are also as simple as a
barrier, that sits between a
home computer and the internet.
Abraham: A DDoS ‘distributed denial
of service’ attack involves multiple
systems orchestrating a synchronised
attack by Botnets [interconnected
devices running software] directing
malicious network traffic or data to
a single target, overloading a server.
These attacks can be seriously disruptive!
Nicole: Cloud technology allows access
to files and services from anywhere
in the world through the internet.
It consists of a collection of
high-capacity storage computers
that remotely work as servers.
Cloud Storage is very popular for the
safe storage of files due to its secure
accessibility anytime through Cloud
services, the infra- structure and
software hosted by a third-party provider.
Cloud services facilitate the flow of
data from the user via the internet
or VPN [virtual private network]
to their systems and back again.
This can offer users, all the
facilities, without all the initial
financial outlay, for a fee depending
on how many services they use.
Abraham: All data needs to be stored
and whether this is in the cloud, in
storage media and/or in transit it
needs to be ‘encrypted’ to be secure.
Encryption is a form of cryptography
where a message is encoded so that
only those who should see it can
access it by means of a ‘key’.
Encryption keys consist of
random strings of unintelligible
numbers, letters, and symbols.
This is done to prevent theft by hackers.
Nicole: BYOD stands for Bring Your
Own Device and involves employees
who use their own devices for work.
With working from home and general
remote working becoming more common,
many individuals have their own
devices that they use for business,
as well as in a personal capacity.
A BYOD policy sets any limitations
and restrictions on whether or not
a personal device can be connected
over the corporate network, depending
on the security systems in place.
More information on this
subject can be seen in our video
on BYOD and remote working.
Check out the link below.
Abraham: We are always hearing about
hackers and how bad they are, but
sometimes hacking can be used for good.
A PenTest or Penetration test is also
classed as ‘ethical hacking’ and is
an authorised simulated cyber attack,
on a computer system using ‘hackers
tools’, to assess whether there are
any exploitable vulnerabilities.
This is different to a ‘vulnerability
assessment’ which identifies,
quantifies, and prioritises
vulnerabilities in a system.
Nicole: Organisations often shift to
different domains for business and
technical reasons and may forget to
renew their older domains but still use
them in their code and infrastructure,
opening themselves up to Domain takeover.
The abandoned domains can offer
attackers an opportunity to take
advantage of this vulnerability.
When an attacker registers the
abandoned domain, they own the domain
and its subdomains and other type
of DNS records and can exploit them.
Pentesters can look for potential
domains that might exist and
be vulnerable to takeover.
Subdomain takeovers generally
occur when a subdomain points to
a service that no longer exists.
An attacker may take it over but
only that subdomain is affected.
We can see through looking at
core terminology, that a Breach
in security can be made by a range
of unauthorised attacks, through a
variety of different means, and can
be on the whole much more damaging
than a physical breach of security.
Cyber criminals have potential access to
everything and often it can be detected
too late to mitigate the effects.